CHRISTIAN MEULI: I saw the cityin the deep, deep distance,
that was dark green, and allthese lights flickering
and clouds flowing over it.
And this all started aftertremendous geometric patterns
that are incredibly rapid thatyou can't describe to anybody,
they're so fast.
After those had slowed down,
I saw this city in thedeep distance.
So I was sort of watching that,and then this ball of light
goes right past me,right in front of me.
What was that?
It didn't scare me,except it was so close.
After that I started lookingaround, and it's like you are
in this place, and then you'regoing "Why am I in this place?"
Then I noticed that there wasthis woman off to my right,
with a real long nose,she had green skin.
She was turning this dial,and I realized she was turning
the volume of lights up and downon the city, in the distance.
And as soon as I looked at her,she noticed I was watching her,
and she said "What elsedo you want?"
And I said, "What elsedo you have?"
JOE ROGAN: This is the storyof DMT, or dimethyltryptamine.
A simple compound foundthroughout nature,
which has profound effectson human consciousness.
DENNIS MCKENNA: One of thethings, besides what it does,
one of the things about DMTthat always fascinated me was
the fact that it's sucha simple molecule.
DAVE NICHOLS: DMT standsfor dimethyltryptamine.
Nn- dimethyltryptamine.
If you actually look at thering structure of DMT itself,
you only have really fourpositions that you can
attach things to.
So you can make diethyl,or dipropyl.
There are some other types ofcarbon chains you can attach
to that end that do give youcompounds that have activity,
but very different from DMT.
DR. MCKENNA: Biosyntheticallyit's two steps from tryptophan.
Right, two trivial enzymaticsteps from tryptophan.
Well tryptophan is an amino acidof course, and it's everywhere,
so all organisms havetryptophan, and all organisms
have the two key enzymes thatlead to the synthesis of DMT.
These enzymes are veryancient enzymes;
they're all over the place.
They're again part of basicmetabolism, so theoretically,
anything could synthesize DMT.
GRAHAM HANCOCK: DMT isastonishingly widely available
in plants and animals allaround the world, but so far,
nobody really knows why it'sthere, or what its function is.
DR. MEULI: That's the 64billion dollar question.
Why is DMT in our bodies?
Why is it in plants?
And all sorts of mammals?
And what is the roleit plays in humans?
DR. MCKENNA: The conventionalwisdom 30 to 40 years ago was
that these things hadno real function.
They were sort of physiologicalnoise, but that's very
naïve understanding.
What we now understand is thatthese secondary compounds are
in a sense the languageof plants.
These are messenger molecules.
This is what plants use tomediate their relationships
with other organismsin the environment.
CHARLES GROB: Why is it thathuman being's central nervous
system are wired toreceive this experience?
Must be that there's importantinformation to be learned.
HANCOCK: So, I don't think it'suniversally present in nature
by accident.
It has a real function.
We have co-evolved with theseplants, there's a purpose
and a meaning to it.
LEANNA STANDISH: So it reallyfits in with the notion that
DMT may be the common molecularlanguage, resonate language,
among all living beings -
on this planet and maybeothers as well.
I can't think of a morepowerful tool to explore
the whole question of"what is consciousness?"
RALPH METZNER: These substancesare tools that can be used to
expand awareness in all areas oflife, and apply that expanded
awareness for the bettermentof peoples' lives.
In their community, theirfamily and our society.
JEREMY NARBY: The good news isthat there's a growing number
of westerners, and actuallyintellectuals, scientists,
artists, movers and shakers,filmmakers, and so on
who realize that this stuff isall too interesting to go on
keeping it swept under the rug?
And meanwhile, the inquisitionwas a long time ago,
the birth of rationalismwas a long time ago.
At this point, there is no goodreason, apart from bad habit,
to keep up these barriers.
ROGAN: With the help of twoconcepts that are
traditionally opposed, scienceand spirituality, we humbly
reintroduce psychedelics backinto the cultural dialogue.
ALEX GREY: DMT, the SpiritMolecule, it's a conundrum,
it's a paradox.
The spirit is the inner world,the molecule is the external
world, so the psychedelics,or entheogens, take us from
the science to the spirit.
RICK STRASSMAN: I was drawn tothe pineal gland, which is a
very small organ in the centerof the brain, which has
always been an object ofinterest, and even veneration
for a lot of esoteric,physiological disciplines.
I thought I wasn't totallycrazy to presume a pineal site
of origin for DMT, which fitin nicely with my theory
that the pineal was somehowinvolved in naturally
occurring mystical states.
JOEL BASKT: This hypothesisproposes that the pineal gland,
at certain times, it's underspecific stress or stimulation
it releases a significantamount of this hormone DMT.
And it's that hormone thatfacilitates the entering
and exiting of the soulin the body.
This is what the Jewish sagemystics have been describing
in a coded language forliterally thousands of years.
DR. STRASSMAN: Throughmeditation, through fasting,
chanting, any number oftechniques, there might be a
burst of endogenous DMT thatwas correlated with mystical
and near-death experiences.
I had this theory that therewas a big similarity between
psychedelics and experiencesthat were possible with
a lot of mediation.
That's one of the originalfindings that led me to start
looking for a spirit molecule,for a compound in the brain
that elicited mysticalexperience.
STEVEN BARKER: I think theremay be a role for DMT in
explaining any number ofhallucinatory phenomenon
that man has experiencedthough out his history.
Creativity, imagination, dreamstates, changes that occur
due to isolation, trauma,starvation, all of which
produce hallucinatoryphenomenon.
These hallucinatory phenomenonare explainable by the presence
of compounds that are known toproduce hallucinations,
and the only compounds that weknow of that are capable of
doing this, are the classof compounds known as
hallucinogens.
ANDREW NEWBERG: When thinkingabout spiritual states,
I think endogenoushallucinogenic compounds
and molecules that the braincan potentially release
are probably very relevant tothis topic because on one hand
they may really help us toelucidate what is the
neurochemical mechanismof these experiences.
I mean if we can say that thereis a release of endogenous
opiates or we can say thatthere's a release of dopamine
or something like that andwe can measure that release
and we can see where in thebrain those different molecules
go, what receptors theyactivate or deactivate,
and hence we can really learna lot more about what these
experiences are because itreally can allow us to match up
these experiences that peoplehave with hallucinogens as well
as understanding where theyare related in the context of
the brain's receptors and thedifferent parts of the brain
that may or may notbecome active.
DR. STRASSMAN: One of the otherinteresting things about the
pharmacology of DMT is thatit's actively transported
into the brain, so you have towonder about the role of DMT
in just every day normalperceptual activity.
Too much DMT and things becomevery psychedelic or not enough
DMT and brain can make thingsdull and flat and grey.
NEAL GOLDSMITH: There'ssomething that for me
makes sense about DMT.
You call it the spirit molecule;
it might almost be calledthe reality molecule.
Philosophically it makes sensethat something that would be
so fundamental to the way weperceive reality would be
imbued out there in reality.
ERIK DAVIS: There was a sensearound it that there was
something special that itwasn't like anything else,
it wasn't like otherpsychedelics,
its intensity and speed wassuch that it really produced
a different kind of response,I mean I remember almost
getting the sense that itwas kind of like a
psychedelic bungee jumpthat there was a kind of
raw leap into this rapidlychanging environment that
was very different than themore gradual approaches
of other psychedelics.
JAMES KENT: To smoke DMT is sortof like the drive by shooting
of psychedelics.
You're in one place BANG you'rein another place and then BANG
you're back down, so it doesn'tleave a whole lot of room for
that narrative of who am I,what am I doing here,
why am I in this space,what am I learning?
It's almost like there was toomuch information to process
in that few minute span tointegrate once you drop
back down.
DR. BARKER: Dimethyltryptaminewhen it's administered has a
very rapid onset and a veryshort duration of action.
This is because it's veryrapidly broken down by the
body so that it can be cleared.
DR. NICHOLS: DMT is rapidlydegraded by an enzyme in the
liver called monoamine oxidase,or MAO, that's the reason
it's not active when youtake it by mouth.
Whereas psilocybin when youtake it by mouth it's not
broken down by monoamineoxidase very quickly at all
so it gets through the liverand passes on into the
bloodstream and into the brain.
DR. STRASSMAN: Yah, I'm veryinterested in Ayahuasca.
When I began my studies in theearly 1990's Ayahuasca was just
starting to make inroads intothe west, but it's obviously
become a lot more popular inthe last 10-15 years and the
visionary ingredientin Ayahuasca is DMT.
Through some amazing feat ofpre literate chemistry,
the Amazonian natives stumbledupon or combined whatever.
I don't know how they did itbut they found that one plant
contains DMT and one plantcontains an enzyme inhibitor;
combine them and you can drinkDMT and it's orally active,
so it starts working in a halfhour and lasts for three
or four hours and you canmaneuver a lot more
comfortably within that statethan you can when you're just
smoking it or injecting it.
KENT: Orally active Ayahuascatends to pick you up and gently
carry you into the space and hugyou and embrace you and clean
you and show you all sorts ofmystical visions and then it
very gently brings you backdown like you're floating
on a feather back to the ground.
KAT HARRISON: As valuable as myDMT experiences have been,
I feel that there is a lot moreenduring value really in this
folk technology which stretchesit out and makes it a
navigable space.
Our whole western Europeanderived tradition of distilling
alcohols and isolating chemicalsand making everything stronger
and taking it out of nature andputting into the biggest punch
that we can, I don't thinkthat generally that's the
most useful way.
I think there's a reason thatcultures have learned to turn
a five minute experience intoa five hour experience.
It seems to me that Ayahuascahas had a plan and that it's
reached out into the world andbrought DMT into many many
thousands of lives and a muchbigger canvas that it had
reached for the last 10,000or however many years.
It's done it very rapidlyand it's done it with
form to go with it.
HANCOCK: Ayahuasca is muchharder for the power structures
that we have now, it's muchharder for them to put down
because it has been part ofa legitimate religious
and spiritual practice forthousands of years,
certainly in the Amazon,and we can't just dismiss
all that as primitive mumbojumbo and superstition.
We have to get to grips withthat on its own terms.
NARBY: I think that there is agrowing number of people who
feel this desire to get back intouch with nature, with plants,
with animals and who know thatthrough the shamanic path there
is a way of doing this and thatactually these tools,
these psychoactive tools fromplants like Ayahuasca is a
very direct way of doing this,now it may not be everybody's
cup of tea and I think a lotof people are actually with
good reason afraid of it.
DAVIS: I think like a lot ofpeople in my generation
I first heard about DMTthrough Terence McKenna.
It was a very funny way tobecome aware of such powerful
and interesting andanthropologically rich topic
as a compound like DMT becauseit really became more, it was
almost more of a concept thansomething that people were
necessarily taking.
TERENCE MCKENNA: The DMT flashmakes it clear that disembodied
consciousness is a possibility;
I think that the whole tension
of history and the tension oflife seems to be about the
shedding of the body.
DR. MCKENNA: Terence was very,he was a good promoter,
basically he said it's theultimate metaphysical reality
pill even though it's not a pillbut, I thought it was a pretty
good characterizationafter I took it.
It seemed to be of a differentorder than LSD and Mescaline
and some of the other thingsthat were around, DMT really
did seem to be a whole otherlevel of experience.
ROGAN: I ask that you suspendany opinions either negative
or positive about thesecompounds.
Whatever you believe their valueto be, they continue to have
profound effects where ever wefind their use, whether it's
contemporary western cultureor in the Amazon rain forest.
METZNER: It was in the 50's thatthe Ayahuasca churches started
going public, there as a kind oftransition from the indigenous
Indians in South America to theMestizo people in the cities
and then these churches you knowthe Santo Daime churches
and the UDV church a littlelater started doing ceremonies
that would make the Ayahuascaaccessible not just to Indians
but to urban people in thebig cities who are as far
from the shamans as we are.
DR. GROB: In the early 1990'sthe UDV established a branch
of their church in theUnited States.
In the late 90's the U.S.customs department along with
the D.E.A. intercepted ashipment of Ayahuasca.
The church protested thegovernment action,
they contended that it violatedthe Religious Freedom
Restoration Act and the casewas heard in the U.S. Supreme
Court and in February 2006their decision was announced
and it was a unanimousdecision on the side of the UDV.
NARBY: Why is it that in theentire western world these
substances that have been foundto be so interesting by hundreds
of cultures for thousandsof years are prohibited.
How did these cultures thatconsider themselves to be
enlightened, democratic, andscientific get to declaring
plants illegal?
It can seem weird but there'sclearly something deep
and revealing about thenature of these societies.
HANCOCK: Our society valuesalert problem solving
consciousness and itdevalues all other
states of consciousness.
Any kind of consciousnessthat is not related to the
production or consumption ofmaterial goods is stigmatized
in our society today.
Of course we accept drunkenness;we allow people some brief
respite from the material grind.
A society that subscribes tothat model is a society that is
going to condemn states ofconsciousness that have nothing
to do with the alert problemsolving mentality, and if you go
back to the 1960's when therewas, you know a tremendous up
surge of exploration ofpsychedelics, I would say that
the huge backlash that followedthat had to do with a fear on
the part of the powers that bethat if enough people went into
those realms and thoseexperiences the very fabric
of the society we have todaywould be picked apart and most
importantly those in power atthe top would not be in power
at the top any more.
DOUGLAS RUSHKOFF: There was anoptimism that was ungrounded,
you know that Vietnam washappening that all this real
stuff was going on and that thepsychedelic movement wasn't
really addressing that in a realway, and that Timothy and that
bunch sold us a false bill ofgoods that didn't really work.
TIMOTHY LEARY: We are now,whether we like it or not,
in the psycho-chemical age.
In the future it's not going tobe what book you read it's going
to be what chemicals do youuse to open or close your
consciousness.
Chemicals can help us learnfaster, chemicals can help us
expand or contractour consciousness.
RALPH ABRAHAM: The atmospherein the 1960's was,
we are doing research here,we are dedicating our lives
to trying just about everythingon the planet.
So we would try it,then we would talk about it,
then we would evaluate it,we regarded ourselves
more or less as spiritualpioneers.
DANIEL PINCHBECK: I mean the wayI look at the 60's; you can see
it as a kind of failed attemptat a mass cultural voyage
of initiation.
You know some people would tryto go out into these other
realities but they didn'thave a basis for it.
There weren't wisdom traditionsand elders, there weren't
connections of shamaniclineages, some people would
go out and kind of smash apart.
ROLAND GRIFFITHS: TimothyLeary really so discredited a
scientific approach to studyingthis because he started off
doing interesting researchand then got into advocating
use in a way that wasincredibly threatening.
Culturally we reacted andpolitically it became impossible
to do this sort of research.
Funding agencies didn'tmake resources available,
regulatory agencies increasedthe practical hurdles for
initiating this kind of researchand I think people who had
interest in research of thistype largely were discredited
because of their interestin the research.
Social, political, scientificissues that came together
pushed these drugs out ofthe scientific marketplace.
DR. BARKER: The public opinionin many cases had become
that psychedelic researchwas dangerous.
The lay public was uninformedabout the true nature of these
compounds and what theirimportance may be in the
understanding ofperception itself.
DR. NICHOLS: One of thetragedies to me is that
the clinical research on thesesubstances pretty much stopped
around 1970, and for me it'sespecially tragic because
I really believe that thesesubstances played a major role
in the development of ourphilosophy and thinking
throughout the world.
What a lot of people don'trealize is that psychiatry
up until the 50's, the fieldin general had no concept that
neurochemistry played any rolein emotion or behavior which
today seems really bizarre andthe discovery of LSD and its
potent effects on the humanpsyche occurred almost
contemporaneously with thediscovery of serotonin as a
molecule in the brain and it wasreally when people looked at
the structure of serotonin andcompared it with LSD that they
really began to think, you knowmaybe neurochemistry plays a
role in brain chemistryand behavioral states.
If LSD had not been discovered,I doubt we would have had any
of the drugs we have at leastnot as quickly as we do for
treating depressionand so forth.
DR. STRASSMAN: Once these drugsbecame abused and scandalized,
psychiatry had to really workhard to distance themselves
from any valid scientific,scientifically meritorious
relationship with psychedelics.
Being a psychiatrist and sayingyou want to learn or study about
psychedelics, it's not that wellreceived and I made one mention
one time and was discouragedfrom really bringing it up again
for actually a number of years.
GRIFFITHS: For cultural reasonsthe whole class of compounds got
pulled off the clinical benchand no research has gone on
for 40 years.
So, scientifically I can'timagine a more exciting area
to be pursuing.
ROGAN: How does one go aboutstudying these plants
and compounds?
Plants and compounds whichproduce unimaginable experiences
and appear to shed light onsome of humanities greatest
mysteries.
In order to answer that questionDr. Strassman conducted the
first human psychedelicresearch in a generation.
DR. STRASSMAN: One of the thingsthat I had established early on
was being able to discriminatebetween studies in the
scientific realm andrecreational use, but in the
early 1980's I reviewed all ofthat literature and could pretty
well establish on that if peoplewere really carefully screened
and supervised and thenfollowed up that the incidents
of adverse reactions to LSDand related psychedelics drugs
was extremely low.
The drug or the compound or thechemical that seemed like the
best candidate to sort ofreopen the U.S. front on
psychedelic researchwould be DMT.
DR. NICHOLS: It was really,it was exciting for me because
this was the first study in ageneration and not only that
despite the fact that DMT hadbeen used safely and in earlier
studies and it was this naturalcomponent of the brain,
DMT is one of the most profoundand potent psychedelics known.
So, it wasn't just an initiationof clinical research it was a
reinitiation of clinic researchwith an extremely potent drug.
I was of the strong opinion thatyou could do these studies
and Rick agreed.
So, we had a number ofdiscussions and at some point
the discussion came up, you knowDave what if I do all this paper
work and spend all this time andget to the end of things and I'm
ready to go and I can't getthe DMT, and that was a real
possibility because DMT,clinical grade DMT wasn't a
chemical you could just buy offthe shelf somewhere, and I told
Rick if you get to that pointand no one will make it then
I'll do it, and ultimately Rickgot to that point and I made it.
DR. STRASSMAN: The designof the study was fairly
straight forward, give peopleDMT and measure as many
variables as possible.
I had to sort of anticipate alot of objections that would
come my way from the regulatoryagencies that oversee
this kind of research.
So that point began a two yearprocess of dealing with not that
many regulatory agenciesbut fairly monolithic ones.
One sort of you knowsatellite of the protocol
was the involvement of apsychiatrist from U.C.L.A.
named Daniel Freedman, he waskind of one of the grand old men
of American psychiatry andactually he was one of the
people who in the 50's and60's got their start with
psychedelic research.
DR. NICHOLS: And the main thingthat Danny Freedman told Rick,
told us, was don't even getclose to psycho therapy.
Forget about treating mentalillness or alcoholism
or anything; forget that,that's where all the hysteria is
that's where all thefears get up.
You're a scientist Rick,approach it as a scientist.
Do basic simple measurements,look at heart rate,
cardiovascular parameters, youwon't get in trouble doing that.
You can get it fundedand it's solid science.
Rick did what he said but thenhe still was able to get these
accounts of what happened, andthat wasn't in the plan that
wasn't really what was proposedin the studies that were funded
and that wasn't what Dannytalked about, but those were
the spin off that reallymade it interesting.
PATRICIO DOMINGUEZ: RickStrassman was advertising in
some magazine somewhere aboutwanting volunteers for a
particular study in apsychotropic, and I didn't
really know what, I didn't knowDMT from STP at that time.
I remember reading that andthinking oh my god this is bad,
I had better get involved inthis and make sure that somebody
doesn't get hurt and that atleast there be some
sensitivity towards what thisstuff is really about.
SUSAN BLUMENTHAL: I met Rick'sresearch nurse at a party
and she heard me talking aboutthat I had used peyote
ceremonially, and she tookme aside and said,
"There's something that youmight be interested in.
"We're looking for subjects,volunteer subjects for some
unusual research."
CYNTHIA GEIST: I was a littleconcerned that the study
participants might be a littleobnoxious, maybe that's not the
right word but, you know peoplethat were just seeking to do a
lot of drugs, and they werevery professional people.
There were varying degrees as tohow much hallucinogen use they
had been through it seemed like,there were some people that it
felt like they had made itkind of their life mission to
experience every kind ofsubstance out there and then
other people who I think werejust interested for their
own personal growthand/or curiosity.
SUSAN: Once we actually gotinto the preparation for the
actual trips, Rick asked meabout roller coasters.
"Do you like roller coasters;you know the sensation of going
up really high and then slammingback down towards earth?"
And I said, "No I hate them,they're horrible" and he said,
"Not good."
I just wanted to go with theexperience, learn as much as
I could, absorb as much asI could and be humble to it.
ANDREW STONE: The idea oflegally sanctioned psychedelics
was just very compelling.
Plus you're in a hospitalso should you get that
uncomfortable experience thatyour dying, your with doctors
in a very safe environmentfrom that point of view.
DR. STRASSMAN: I mean this isreally very cutting edge,
very out there, very, it washigh risk and people knew what
they were getting into and theywanted to have the extra
reassurance and I was gladactually to have a crash cart
in the room and a team inthe hospital to respond
to any emergencies.
SUSAN: Your in this hospitalroom and there's all the sounds
and the smells and just theprior experiences of being in
the hospital you know, all thesenegative things come back so
there was the whole environmentto be overcome because little
did I know that it didn'tmatter where I was,
I wasn't going to be in my body.
I was going to be out in theuniverse and it didn't matter
where you launched from it couldbe a hospital room it could be
the jungle in the Amazon itdidn't matter where you were
because you weren't goingto stay there.
PATRICIO: Set and setting isSO important it's even more
important than the substance,more important than the
substance.
Set and setting is everything.
Now what is the set and settingwhen you are blindfolded?
The set and setting is notwhat you're seeing
you're not seeing anything.
The set and settingis your internal self.
The things that you havelearned, the capacities that you
have achieved the conditions ofyour own psyche and psychology;
these are your set and setting.
ROBERT WEISZ: It's the medicinecombined with or interacting
with the set and setting thatcreates an effect of safety
of trust of comfort and ofresourcefulness that makes it
possible for you to take somebig leaps and receive some big
gifts and if that's not thereyou just get terrified.
CYNTHIA: So, I didn't reallyhave physical fears so much that
they would die or have a stroke.
I did have some fears aboutpeople's mental health,
especially with someof the higher doses.
We gave one gentlemen who had alot of experience with the drug
one dose and he didn't think ittook him far enough so then we
gave him a higher dose and hewas gone, he was really gone.
It reminded me of something fromthe exorcist, I mean he just
sat bolt up in the bed and hiseyes opened up and they were
completely dilated and black andI almost thought he was going to
turn his head completely aroundand I remember looking at Rick
and Rick looking at me and Ithought "Oh My God he's gone,
I hope he comes back,and he did."
ANTONAPAULOS SPIROS: Thecountdown was like counting
down, preparing for your deathlike waiting to surrender
and you feel the coldness andthe coldness just going through
your veins, and it's reallyindescribable, it's hard to;
it's like ice goingthrough your veins.
The next thing that would happenbesides my racing heart is this
burning sensation would happenon the back of my neck,
I mean this was reliablethis was like clockwork.
This happened every time thatyou shot me up with DMT
and then there would be a humand the hum would get louder
and get louder, and to the pointwhere it broke apart everything
that I was or knew, It wasjust this (hummmmm)
It just got louder and louderuntil you just had to
surrender to the sound,
and then you were there.
DR. MEULI: I would get a warmfull feeling, a golden feeling
in my chest beforeit went to my head.
I would feel this warm rod aboutan inch and a half in diameter
start growing up insidemy central channel.
It would come up and sort ofslow, warm up my chest go up
through my head and slow downand put tremendous pressure in
my sinuses behind my eyes andslow down and start to grow
and extend the skin behindmy forehead about one inch
behind my hairline.
I was afraid it was going to popmy skin a few times because it
was a very physical feeling.
About an inch and a half,two inches above my skull,
when it popped through therethen the psychedelic trip
would start.
I thought I had died.
I saw the white clouds, therenaissance white fluffy clouds
with the gods and the angels andall that stuff is what I saw.
I thought I was dying and goingout but I did take a quick look
at Cynthia and a quick look atRick because I had my eyes open
and they were both therewatching looking there
very calmly.
I go whew that's really goodnews, my body looks fine.
STONE: So, I didn't knowwhether it was my birth I was
re-experiencing, my death whichwas yet to come because
I know that time crumbles, thelinearity of time is totally
meaningless in these states,you are at the god head,
the point where all timefolds in on itself.
PATRICIO: More and more layersof my humanity start
peeling off.
Finally, the last, no almostthe last layer and I can't even
describe what it is but youhave, at some reaches way
in there there is like the lastlayer of that which defines you
as a human being,and it goes click.
You are no longer a human being;
in fact you are no longeranything you can identify.
SUSAN: There was no concept oftime, it was so disorienting.
I was so terrified, I havenever in my entire life been so
terrified to be blasted out ofmy body, to leave my body behind
to be going at warp speedbackwards through my own DNA
out the other end intothe universe.
DR. MEULI: And so I went rightinto this white light,
as soon as I went into it I lostany sense of being different,
any sense of what I was doing,past, any sense of future.
It was absolutely blissful andeuphoric and I just felt like,
it wasn't I, I waseverything I was the light.
There was no sense ofseparation, no shadows,
no differences, no past,no future.
It was all present andwhite yellow light.
Then I felt myself falling outof this light and as I fell out
of it I could feel the light waslike a glow like the sun with
flames coming out and lappingout and I could already start to
feel this tremendous separation.
SUSAN: I reached across and itwas suddenly I'm in the universe
in this huge void with thesebeings on the other side
and I put out my hands and thisincredible rainbow of pink light
went between me and theseentities and I was trying to
make it be like a white lightbut it was this incredible pink
light, this energy of love thatwe, this capacity of love that
we as human beings have that Iwas trying to just send to them.
PATRICIO: This meteor like tripthrough the infinite space of
the interior consciousness is,up pops the picture puzzled
pattern door and I'm nowwhizzing through this sucker
like if it was nothing it justI'm flying through it,
but now I know what the picturepuzzle pattern door is.
The picture puzzle pattern dooris the farthest reaches
of your humanity.
This is the doorway into thewhat defines you as
a human being.
When you go past that you stopbeing human to a degree and the
further you get past this pointthe further away you go from
being a human being, but righthere this picture puzzle pattern
door is everything.
Its everything, it's whatdefines you as a human being,
this is your, this picturepuzzle pattern door is YOU.
STONE: This is like the actualcore of where all of reality is
emanating from.
This is wheremeaning comes from.
Symbols where pouring out, theywere intertwined every symbol
and letter and in every languagewas pouring out of this point.
SUSAN: And I looked around at myenvironment and I was trying to
absorb everything to understandbut there were all of these
machines or structures or thingsthat I had never seen before
that I had no idea what theywere and I was like a cave man
in a computer lab.
I didn't have any idea butI knew in my intellectual
awareness that this was a veryadvanced civilization or life
forms, or whatever they were,they were so far advanced from
what we know here on earth.
STONE: There's one state in it,I call it the hobby horses
and they're interlockingreticulating vibrating hobby
horses and I use that, that'swhat they seem like to me.
They interlock and they forma visual pattern that seems
infinite in scape and thenyou're on the inside outside
inside every side and so it'sless possible to use,
you know words startto escape you.
SPIROS: The texture of thespace was very much like an
animated Mexican tile.
It seemed to be hyper vivid incolor in a Technicolor sense
but also very clay likeand earthen, you know like
with an earthen...
pointing towards earth butnot really being of earth.
WEISZ: There was no eye.
There was just a sense of awitness being suspended in this
incredible vaulted space like acathedral made out of a stained
glass out of all imaginablecolors, unbelievable brilliance
and saturation of color justthis amazing pattern in this
dome, this gigantic dome.
It felt like the size of a smallplanet and there were these
winged beings.
I don't remember exactly whatthey looked, but they were like
angels, something like angels,that were majestically kind of
flying through the space butthere was something about
the quality of how they wereflying that was unique.
I had never seenanything like it.
It was like I don't know;it was the sense of another
realm that was there.
My sense was, at some pointthere was this implicit sense
this is the divine realm, thisis the divine realm, and it was
not like a thought but it waslike this implicit kind of
groching recognition.
SUSAN: It was all very veryimpersonal until I got to the
space where I realized that Iwas in the area where souls
await rebirth, and I was thereand I had been there so many
times before I recognized it andthis incredible transcendent
peace came over me.
I have never in my lifeever felt such peace.
Everything was stripped away,every hope, every fear,
every attachment to thematerial world was completely
stripped out of me.
I was free to just be theessence of a soul.
WEISZ: After the medicine woreoff there is that familiar
sensation of kind ofcoming back into the body.
I do remember that, that waspart of almost all of those
experiences of kind ofcoalescing back into sensory
awareness and a sense of havinga body and of that becoming a
little more substantial and thenI say, "Oh yeah here I am
and I live in a bodyand I'm OK."
PATRICIO: So, Laura removes theeyeshades, and I ask not really
with my eyes open quite yet, Iask how long was I gone because
I needed to know, and Rickchimes in, "Like 15 minutes".
For a moment I'm shocked,I'm like you know,
my mind has to try to catch upbecause now the whole cognitive
dissonance of the experiencehas to, has to catch up.
I was gone for 15 minutes.
A thousand years ofexperience in 15 minutes.
Well to say the leastit was profound.
It was, it was profound.
CYNTHIA: It's amazing;it's amazing what a human being
can experience in ahospital bed.
I mean they can experiencealmost the whole universe,
life, death, everythingin between.
STONE: This is not somerecreational thing,
and I don't believe anybodyshould enter this lightly.
It is life transformative.
It will perhaps shake you enoughto realize that you need to be
awake to the fact that you don'tknow and that is the beginning
of starting to know.
SUSAN: What we see here is sucha tiny part of what is real.
I get really frustrated becauseof course there is no way to
prove that where I went was deepspace that I encountered other
entities, other life formsthat exist in this universe.
At some point maybe ourcivilization will become
advanced enough and we willthrow off these anchors of
impossible thought that thesethings are impossible that it's,
it's not, you know thateverything that exists,
exists where we can see it.
DR. STRASSMAN: I wrapped upthe studies in '95 and really
just had to take a breakfor a couple of years.
I was aware of a growing senseof discomfort with what I was
doing because I justcouldn't explain it.
It seemed to me if I couldn'tmodel and explain what was
going on that I was doing andjust bringing people to the edge
of these kinds of experiencesit seemed like I ought to,
that it was a littleirresponsible to be sort of
pushing people off the clifflike that without really knowing
exactly what it was andaccepting and understanding
and feeling comfortablewith that model.
I think what began dawning on meafter awhile once I stopped
the study was that I wasreally dealing with a
spiritual phenomenon.
ROGAN: What do these experiencessay about the nature of reality,
the nature of our minds or thefunction of our brain that we
can so quickly shift intothese alternate realities?
Let's take a step back andconsider how these experiences
inform us about ourselves,our consciousness
and the symbiosis of the two.
DR. STRASSMAN: It startedseeming to me that what was
happening with DMT, particularlywith respect to some of these
reports of entering parallelor alternate or free standing
parallel sorts of realmsof existences,
that that indeed was what theirconsciousness was doing.
The chemistry of their brain,which is the organ of
consciousness was being changedby DMT in such a way that they
could then receive informationthat we weren't able
to receive normally.
JOEL BAKST: Yes there's theexperiences from DMT
and Ayahuasca and theyhave their function,
but if we also look at whatit enables us to see.
DR. MCKENNA: It just rips thatfiltering mechanism away for a
few minutes and for a fewminutes you're immersed in
sort of this raw data sphereof input, of sensory input,
of memories of associations.
It seems like the brain buildsreality out of these things;
what your experiencing, what youhave experienced and how you
associate and synthesize thesethings together to tell yourself
a story essentially about what'sgoing on, where you are
in space and time.
DR. NEWBERG: It's the brain thathelps us to process all this
information and to create for usa rendition of what our world
is all about but we'retrapped within that brain.
However, in spiritualexperiences where people feel
that they get beyond the selfand certain types of psychedelic
experiences where you haveincredible sensory and other
types of phenomenon peoplereally feel like they are
able to kind of get outsideof their brain.
We have to take a very big lookat what is going on within them
when they have the experienceand try to understand how it
happens physiologically andtry to make sense of it
from the subjective perspectiveas well as from the
objective perspective.
I don't think you can just saylet's just explain it away on
the basis of science.
DR. STRASSMAN: What I was doingearly on when I was hearing
these reports were interpretingthem calling them psychological
or brain chemistry aberrationsor whatever, that there was a
part of the brain that was beingdinged that was responsible for
the alien appearance phenomenon.
DR. BARKER: This is not a newphenomenon; entities in altered
states have been recognizedfor an extremely long time,
in many cultures overthe millennia.
Helpers, spirit, assistants,angels all of these different
entities have been fairly commonthroughout man's experience of
altered states and throughmuch of man's mythology.
DR. NICHOLS: But I don't thinkit's out of the realm of
possibility that people are insome way interacting with some
sort of an intelligence orsentient being or something
that exists at some level that'snot in this three dimensional
physical plane.
RUSHKOFF: I'm looking at itfrom a sense of
"OK, is the drug healing you?
"Is it helping you and isit giving you the tools?
What are you bringing back?"
What you bring back I think hasto be something more than,
there are these entitiesout there.
The best psychedelic explorersare people who realize that even
the truths they see ona trip are not truths,
but new models, new what ifs,alternative frames.
BAKST: Unless there is a mapand a clear methodology then
one will just have a varietyof different experiences.
All these various experiencesthat have been reported from
NDE's, near death experiences,alien abductions,
alien encounters, sexualecstasy, I believe all of
these experiences in factare fractals.
If we understand the concept offractal geometry, no matter how
small it is, it containseverything that is in the larger
picture and thus that validatesprofoundly all these
various experiences.
DR. STRASSMAN: To discount thephenomenon as hallucinatory
or imaginary, I think it's maybemore useful to look at a
mechanism of action.
If it is real thenperhaps how does it work?
DAVIS: Look there'sextraordinarily regular
phenomenon that come up withthese things that are clearly
linked in many ways to theselarger human issues around
mysticism or religiousexperience or encounters with
other entities and here we haveit and if you can't go in there
and really go in there andaccount for this material inside
your neuroscientific framework your leaving a huge gap.
You've got to account for thisstuff the way you have to
account for dreams the way youhave to account for all sorts
of psychoactive responses.
DR. STRASSMAN: Using DMT as anexplanatory model as kind
of the mediator betweenour consciousness and the
consciousness of a non corporealsort of reality, it's handy.
DR. ABRAHAM: With DMT there areno words, I would try to wrap a
mathematical vocabulary aroundthe experience afterwards.
I specialized in the metaphor ofvibration and how vibrations in
fluids created form in fluid andthat would be the key to the
relationship betweenthe spiritual realm
and the ordinary realm.
This was the windowthat was opened by DMT.
DR. NEWBERG: Using psychedelicsdrugs or other types of
pharmacological substances canhelp to induce a state where
people feel that they touch adeeper sense of reality where
they understand reality on amore fundamental level and they
gain a great deal of insight andknowledge into the ways in which
the world works and how they areas a human being supposed to
relate to that world.
DR. ABRAHAM: DMT is somehow itseems to me in my experience
more of a breakthrough than LSD,mushrooms, peyote and so on.
It's instructive, it's moresupportive of future evolution
and the creation of thefuture and it is in itself
more of a mystery.
How could this little stuffproduce something that has
intelligence?
It is actually a doorway into another reality.
DR. NEWBERG: So, what is thenature of reality and what is
the nature of how we ashuman beings experience it?
Can we understand it better?
Are we capable of understandingreality on some very fundamental
levels and what do we need todo to be prepared for that?
DR. STRASSMAN: You know, thereare parallel universes it seems;
at least that's a theoryin modern physics.
There is dark matter,which is a huge amount of
the matter of the universemaybe 95% or more.
As radical an idea, is just alogical extension in some ways
of instead of using a machine tosee more than we can normally
can see we're using the brain.
DR. ABRAHAM: There are fieldswhich are undiscovered so far,
which have nothing to do withanything that is discovered
so far.
The gravitation field wasunknown before the year 1604...
the electromagnetic fieldsunknown before the year 1830
or something, all of these whatwe call fundamental fields of
mathematical physicsare new discoveries.
Dark energy is of even newerdiscovery and beyond that are
maybe more discoveries yetcoming beyond our cosmos itself,
and higher dimensionsas they say.
LEANNA SLANDISH: I still don'thave very much use for the
concept of God, but I do believethat there are higher levels,
transcendent levels of realityand I'm actually now starting to
really believe that the brain isnot the source of consciousness,
is not really who we are butis more like a radio tuner
for something way bigger.
DR. NEWBERG: Are theseexperiences spiritual
experiences or otherwise arethey created by physiological
processes or is the brain itselfresponding to something that's
going on and the fact thatsomebody may actually find
a way of turning on their brainto spiritual experiences,
again I'm not sure thatnecessarily diminishes the
reality or the realness of whatthose experiences are about.
If the pharmacology orthe psychopharmacology of
psychedelic experiences turnedout to be essentially the same
as religious or spiritualexperiences, it would help us
to understand where theseexperiences are occurring
within the human brain.
DR. GRIFFITHS: I'm actuallyquite, quite convinced that
we're probing the biologicalbasis of moral
and ethical behavior.
I think these primary religiousexperiences really are at the
bedrock of theworld's religions.
BAKST: The research andknowledge and speculation about
the pineal body and DMT is infact the hand of god that is
interacting with our naturalevolution to stimulate
and accelerate the process ofredemption of individual
and of collectiveglobal enlightenment.
DR. SLANDISH: Because ofmy Ayahuasca experiences,
I consider myself aspiritual person.
I know things now that I couldnever have known otherwise.
DR. ABRAHAM: This experienceis so familiar for a lot of
different people and is soeasily acquired and so much
information comes with so littleeffort that it is a kind of a
miracle it's a miraculous wayfor us to transcend ordinary
reality and obtain maybean intimation of what's
necessary for survival.
ROGAN: Ranging from new forms ofmedical treatment to a better
understanding of the universeto life changing spiritual
revelations, these naturaltools offer us the ability
to seek greater knowledge.
Tools that could positivelyaffect life on our planet.
Let's answer Dr. Strassman'squestion, if so, so what?
BAKST: Because of thecollapse of consciousness,
spiritual and scientificknowledge split apart.
Both these modes of knowing haveto come together, in other words
science and technology froma traditional religious
perspective is not an extra.
It is part of the process bywhich humanity is going to
evolve into its next stage.
PINCHBECK: How do we find theright form for psychedelics
in the future?
Assuming psychedelics arepart of the human future,
at the moment they're stillgenerally repressed
and suppressed and illegal.
If that were to change, howwould we begin to construct
a kind of system that wouldallow for a rational mature
exploration of psychedelics?
NARBY: I think the name of thegame is to show science the
pertinence of this somewhatoutlandish realm, and it's
not just crazy stuff thatshouldn't be considered as,
let's say not even worthy ofinterest or illegitimate.
I actually think because it'sdeclared off bounds it just
makes it interesting to startwith, but one doesn't want to
throw out the baby with the bathwater and I think it's really
important to stayfaithful to science.
DR. MCKENNA: What does it mean?
Why is there a part of the brainthat seems to be for lack of a
better word, a god detector?
What's the evolutionaryadvantage to having some part of
the brain that seems to triggerand mediate experiences
of the transcendent?
BAKST: The kabala is revealingto us that the pineal body
is actually the very edge of thehigher dimension that is
penetrating into our lowerdimension and it is located
precisely in the middleof the brain.
DR. SLANDISH: I can rememberreading about Descarte thinking
that it was actually theinterface between the spiritual
dimension and the dimension ofmatter and I remember studying
that as a foolish idea fromour history and now it seems
actually like a veryinteresting idea.
BAKST: What we are looking forout there is really in here.
It is the doorway,it is the gate.
DR. GOLDSMITH: So, we focus onthe transformative effect of the
psychedelics, but it's also truethat the reverse is true that
it requires transformation inorder to embrace psychedelics.
It's one of the tricky paradoxesof post modernism that
psychedelics both require andproduce a transformative effect.
HANCOCK: We have severed ourconnection to spirit,
that's what our societyhas done.
It has sought to persuade usthat the material realm is the
only realm, and the only waywe're going to recover is to
reconnect with spirit and Itruly believe that we need
the help of the plantsin order to do that.
KAT: Part of our work is torespect these medicines
and then to change the cultureenough that people doing them
can be respected and held, andnot everybody needs to do them
not everyone should or wants to,but that it isn't pushed to the
side and so part of that doesinvolve then research because
that's how in our reductionistsociety we validate things.
DR. GROB: With the passing ofthe years and the opportunity
for subtle reflection, I thinkthat there is growing
appreciation that there may besomething to gain from studying
these compounds, that there's alot that we can learn and there
may very well may be treatmentmodels particularly for patient
populations for whomconventional treatments
are ineffective for whomthe psychedelic model when
utilized optimally mayprovide great benefit.
DR. SLANDISH: I think the mostimportant thing that we could do
right now that would be fairlystraight forward to do is to
ask and answer the question ofwhether Ayahuasca could help
people who have drugand alcohol abuse.
Given that we know that DMT andsimilar alkaloids have a very
strong effect on the samereceptor sites that are
involved in depression and thenotion that most people,
in my experience, who use drugsand alcohol, are self medicating
a deep depression or an anxiety.
DR. GROB: I've had permissionnow, over the last few years
to utilize psilocybin, whichis the active alkaloid in
hallucinogenic mushrooms, inthe treatment of patients with
advanced stage cancer who haveanxiety, we're treating the
anxiety not the cancer.
Now, psilocybin is4-phosphoryloxy-N,
N-dimethyltryptamin soobviously from a chemical
structure point of view,very similar to DMT.
DR. NICHOLS: Ultimately what Iwant to do is see these things
used in the way that theywere used traditionally,
to heal people, help peopleand right now helping people
come to terms with dying.
STONE: It changes your wholerelationship to your death,
your impending death.
Believe it or not you're goingto die, and now with this tool
of having crossed over alreadysome of the fear around that
will disappear.
DR. SLANDISH: Now I'm beginningto wonder whether consciousness
may actually survive biologicaldeath; that maybe the model that
we've been working under inpsychiatry and behavioral
pharmacology model is justwrong, it's backwards actually
that consciousness isprimary in the universe
and matter is a result of.
DR. GROB: Utilizing substanceslike DMT or 5-methoxy-DMT,
may really help us prepareby practicing a transient
dying experience.
Thus far we're observing verypositive effects in regards to
the nature of the experienceduring the session and then
subsequent effects on moodregulation and anxiety control,
pain perception and overallquality of life for
cancer patients.
By and large our subjects doquite well in the time
they have remaining.
DR. NICHOLS: For those peoplewho do come to terms with it,
part of it is a recognition thatthese psychedelics open up a
space that they weren't awareexisted and sort of give them
a vision of what could be pastdeath as well as a better
perspective on theaccomplishments they've made in
life a better feeling about whatthey've done in their own lives.
DR. ABRAHAM: I think all peoplewho have psychedelic trips
and meditations and so on arepoking more or less into the
same higher realm and receivingsome information there
and develop this into, thiscan be absorbed into ordinary
science that we can approachwith the scientific method
and so on then our intelligenceour capability of survival on
planet earth will be increased.
We're a dying species,we live on a dying planet,
we're killing the planet so ourdisease is extremely serious.
Therefore, we're desperateto find new information,
ideas and so on that cantranscend, we have to evolve
and I think our intellectualevolution may be predicated
upon the psychedelic pioneers.
RUSHKOFF: It's so easy to changethe world, that's the kind of
thing that you can see onpsychedelics if you don't get
trapped in the beauty and aweof the psychedelic experience
itself.
It's like looking through thechandelier of reality from a
different vantage point.
You can now project throughthose crystals in another way
and its beautiful, but OK nowcome back, now come back.
DR. STRASSMAN: I think if I everwere to resume giving people
psychedelics particularly DMTit wouldn't be just to kind of
tinker with brain chemistryjust see what's happening.
I think one of the things I alsolearned in the research is that
you just don't wanna givedrugs and see what happens,
that's a little I don't knowif callous is the word
but that's the first wordthat comes to mind.
I think if you're really gonnaopen people up like that you
need to do it for a purpose notjust for scientific curiosity,
and I'd like to be helpfulrather than just sort
of smart or clever.
DAVIS: To my mind there isthis kind of two edge sword
simultaneously opening up to thenuminous world, to the world of
messages, the world of spirits,the world of entities and at the
same time rigorously taking thatmaterial into the acid bath of
neurology into sociology, intothe ongoing construction of
reality and that the wisdom thatthings bring is this kind of
very tricky mixture of authenticreligious experience with gods,
and messages, and clear signs,and a sort of remarkable
mirror of the mind.
HANCOCK: The curiosity, perhapsthe uniqueness of the human
creature is that we live in bothrealms, we have the ability
for spiritual experienceand we have the ability
for physical experience.
The agenda of the spirit world,if there is an agenda,
is to allow us to experience ourfull potential and to deliver
our full potential and maybethe choices that we are making
right now as a civilizationand a society rebound
far beyond ourselves.
DR. MCKENNA: I think DMT is aforcible reminder that there's
a lot more about reality,the universe, ourselves,
the biosphere, whatever,that there's a lot more to it
than we imagine.
ROGAN: It seems our realityis not the only reality.
Occasionally the cracks revealthemselves and may even
want to be discovered.
As humans we are creaturesthat thirst for knowledge.
We spend time, money, andinfinite energy searching
for it in schools, churches,business, and in technology.
Knowledge is power, andthus our greatest quest.
Dimethyltryptamine, a moleculewith a complex name and the
simplest ability to unlock thedoor to another dimension
and perhaps, just perhaps,our future evolution.